Guide to the Bert Cochran Papers TAM.205
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Bert Cochran Papers
1935-1978
1935-1955
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Cochran, Bert, 1913-1984.
Cochran, Cynthia
TAM.205
2.25 Linear Feet (5 boxes)
Bert Cochran (1916-1984) was a Trotskyist active in the Communist League of America (1934), the Workers Party of the United States (1935-37), in the Appeal Group within the Socialist Party, and in the automobile industry (1930s-40s), first in Cleveland within the Mechanics Educational Society of America, then in Detroit as head of the Socialist Workers Party Auto Fraction and as an activist in the United Automobile Workers of America. He left/was expelled from the SWP in 1954 for his leading role in the "Cochran-Clarke" faction, then helped found the magazine The American Socialist(1954-1959), and subsequently wrote seven books that covered labor and economics, and current domestic and international affairs. The collection contains correspondence, minutes, and reports relating to his labor and political activities, typescripts of speeches on various topics, and an (incomplete) untitled manuscript, a Marxist history of warfare and society.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Materials were found in repository; provenance is unknown but were likely donated by Cynthia Copeland Cochran in 1998. The accession number associated with these materials is 1998.004.
Arrangement
Within each series, the folders are arranged chronologically.
Organized into three series:
Missing Title
1. Labor and Political Activities
2. Unpublished Writings.
3. Addendum
Historical/Biographical Note
Bert Cochran (Dec 25, 1916 - Jun 4, 1984), an American Trotskyist, also known by the pseudonym, E. R. Frank, was born Alexander Goldfarb in Warsaw, Poland. He joined the Communist League of America in 1934, was a member of the American Workers Party (1935-1937), was a district organizer for the Cleveland district of the Mechanics Educational Society of America (MESA) in 1936-37 and was a member of the Appeal Group (within the Socialist Party), was a member of the Socialist Workers Party (SWP) from its inception in 1938, serving on its National Committee for many years and, based in Detroit, was a leading figure in the SWP's work in organizing auto workers, serving as chair of the SWP's Auto Fraction, and was an activist in the United Automobile Workers of America.
He left/was expelled from the SWP in 1954 for his leading role in the "Cochran-Clarke" faction, which held dissenting views on the appropriate relationship to Stalinism, and in particular to Communist Party labor- movement activism and activists. Along with fellow ex-SWP members George Clarke and Harry Braverman, he founded the magazine The American Socialist(1954-1959). In 1949 he met his companion Cynthia Copeland Cochran (who is also the sister of Vince Copeland, also a Trotskyist activist and long-time leading figure in the Workers World Party).
Cochran wrote seven books. Two were on the labor movement: American Labor at Midpassage(1959) and Labor and Communism: The Conflict that Shaped American Unions(1977). The others were: The Cross of the Moment(1961), The War System(1965), Adlai Stevenson: Patrician among the Politicians(1969), Harry Truman and the Crisis Presidency(1973), and Welfare Capitalism--and After(1984).
Related Material at the Tamiment Library/Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
George Breitman Papers (TAM 169)
Scope and Content Note
This collection is organized into two series: 1. Labor and Political Activities, and 2. Unpublished Writings. The collection contains correspondence, manuscripts, and minutes, reports, and other internal documents, principally from the Socialist Workers Party, and from the United Automobile Workers union. In addition to Cochran (often as E. R. Frank, or as "Burt" Cochran), notable correspondents and authors include George F. Addes, James Burnham, James Cannon, George Clarke, Farrell Dobbs, Vincent R. Dunne, Jules Geller, Rose Karsner, Homer Martin, Felix Morrow, A.J. Muste, Max Shachtman, Arne Swabeck, and Natalia Trotsky. There are also letters from SWP and UAW activists.
In the first series, the American Workers Party file (1935-36) contains discussion of the political and tactical issues involved in the "French Turn" (the mass entry of individual Trotskyists into the Socialist Party, so called after the tactic used in France). The bulk of the series provides concerns the SWP's activity within the automobile industry and the UAW, and the debates within the SWP on these matters. The documentation is most extensive for the years through 1943. There are lengthy analytical letters, confidential reports, club and auto fraction meeting minutes, leaflets and flyers distributed to the rank and file, and some UAW correspondence, minutes and other internal documents. Issues/events covered include: SWP internal debates on automobile industry and general labor union policy, UAW factionalism, 1937-39, and the SWP's initial support for President Homer Martin's faction, organizing auto workers, the conditions and status of auto industry workers employed under the Works Progress Administration (WPA), and responses to labor measures adopted by the U.S. government during World War II.
There are also numerous reports and statements on the international political and military situation during World War II, two letters from/regarding the (Trotskyist) Internationale Kommunisten Deutschlands (International Communist Party of Germany), and a copy of a 1944 letter from Natalia Trotsky relating to the nature of the Soviet Union. The post-World War II files contain reports and speeches and focus on national and international politics, notably Poland, Korea, and for Yugoslavia, a report from an SWP member who had visited Belgrade ca.1950. There is detailed discussion from 1945-46 of the political differences between the SWP majority and the Morrison (nee Albert Goldman) / Felix Morrow minority. There are also typescripts of several of Cochran's speeches from the 1950s on U.S. and international affairs.
Series two contains portions of two unpublished (and untitled and undated) manuscripts. The first is a partial manuscript (some 450 pp.), an explicitly Marxist study of warfare in human history that may have been written in the years preceding Cochran's study of post-World War II world politics and military policy, The War System(Macmillan, 1965). The second consists of one chapter, titled "Workers and Intellectuals" (ca.1978), from an untitled work.
Seeries three (unprocessed) contains correspondence, reports, manuscripts and clippings, most from the end of World War II through 1954, with a few earlier items. Major topics are internal debates within the Socialist Workers Party in the 1950s, including in regard to the "Pabloist" tendency, and the post-War labor movement. Among the manuscripts are several chapters from an untitled work by Cochran.
Manuscripts for publication.; Minutes (administrative records); Reports.; Speeches.; War and society |x History.; Labor unions and communism -- United States.; Socialism -- United States -- 20th century.; Correspondence.; Automobile industry workers |x Labor unions |z United States.; Communism -- United States -- 20th century; Socialist Workers Party; International Union, United Automobile Workers of America (CIO); International Union, United Automobile, Aircraft, and Agricultural Implement Workers of America; Martin, Warren Homer, 1902-1968; Mechanics Educational Society of America; Morrow, Felix; Internationale Kommunisten Deutschlands; Goldman, Albert; Shachtman, Max, 1903-1972; Karsner, Rose.; Swabeck, Arne; Dunne, Vincent R. (Vincent Raymond), 1889-1970; American Workers Party; Geller, Jules; Addes, George F., 1910; Dobbs, Farrell; Burnham, James, 1905-1987; Trotskaia, Nataliia Ivanovna, 1882-1962; Muste, A. J. (Abraham John), 1885-1967.; Cannon, James Patrick, 1890-1974; Clarke, George, 1840-1906; Cochran, Cynthia
- Series 1: Labor and Political Activities
  - United Automobile Workers Union, 1935 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - American Workers PartyContents Include: Cochran Correspondence, Internal Documents. (Correspondents include: James Cannon, George Clarke, Rose Karsner, A.J. Muste, Max Shachtman, Arne Swabeck), 1935-1936 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Mechanics Educational Society of America (MESA): Cochran Correspondence with Matthew Smith (National Secretary)., 1935-1937 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Unemployed Movement Activity - Ohio, New York, 1935-1940 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Cochran: Notes (Midland Steel Strike); Speech (The Flint Sit-Downs: The Spirit of 1937) (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Socialist PartyContents Include: National Auto League Conference (Detroit, May 22-23) Minutes (participants included Victor Reuther and Walter Reuther); Unsigned letter (Nov 25, from Farrell Dobbs?) re Minneapolis Teamsters Movement., 1937 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - United Automobile Workers Correspondence (Includes: Cochran, George F. Addes, Homer Martin), 1937 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Socialist Workers PartyContents Include: Cochran Correspondence (includes letters from James Cannon and George Clarke, and one from James Burnham); Minutes of National Auto Fraction Meeting (Detroit, Dec 25th)., 1938 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - United Automobile Workers: Cochran Correspondence (principally with activists); Homer Martin memorandums; Internal Documents including Unity Caucus material., 1938 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Anti-Communist Party Leaflets for Auto Workers (by Homer Martin supporters), 1938-1939 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Revolutionary Workers League. Cleveland Unit: An Open Letter to All Delegates to the UAW-CIO Convention., 1939 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - United Automobile WorkersContents Include: Cochran Correspondence; Cleveland Convention (March) and Other Factional Materials., Jan 1939-May 1939 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Clarke, George: The Truth About the Auto Crisis: The Petty-Bourgois Leaders Before the Test of the Class Struggle (contra Shachtman, et al - 22 pp), ca.1939 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Robins, Harold: Some of Our Opportunist Mistakes in the Auto Union (19 pp), ca.1939 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Socialist Workers PartyContents: National Auto Conference Minutes, Detroit, May 5th; Pre-Plenum Discussion Bulletin vol. 3, no. 3, September; Correspondence and other documents), 1940 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - United Automobile Workers, 1940 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Socialist Workers PartyContents Include: Cochran correspondence, including James P. Cannon, C. Charles, Vincent Dunne, Jules Geller, automobile industry rank and file activists; Club Executive Minutes; Draft of Revised Declaration of Principles., 1941 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Socialist Workers PartyContents Include: Correspondence (including Cannon, Cochran, Dobbs, Dunne, Jules Geller, G. Munis (Mexico, D.F.); 1942 Report of Outgoing Executive Board Detroit Branch; Resolutions. (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - United Automobile Workers: Cochran correspondence, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - [Cochran]: Report on the U.S. Political Situation (30 pp.), ca.1942-1943 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Socialist Workers PartyContents Include: Correspondence and Reports re Auto Fraction (George [Clarke?], Cochran, Dobbs, rank and file, etc.); Resolution on U.S. and Second World War., 1943 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Morrow, Felix -- The First Phases of the Coming European Revolution: a criticism of the fifteenth anniversary plenum [19 pp], Dec 1943-Jan 1944 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Labor Movement, Reports on [E.R. Frank, J. Lyons, anonymous], 1943-1945 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Socialist Workers Party Contents Include: Correspondence and Reports on Polish, German and Other International Issues - includes two letters (from/regarding) the Internationale Kommunisten Deutschlands (International Communist Party of Germany)., 1944 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - The European Revolution and Tasks of the Revolutionary Party (45 pp) -- SWP National Committee Plenum Resolution, Aug 1944 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Trotsky, Natalia: Letter "Dear Friend" (the USSR no longer even a "degenerating" workers state), 2 pp., Aug 16, 1944 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Cannon, James P.: Letters re Fight Against the Morrison/Morrow Faction (to Larry Trainor, Murry Weiss, and J. Andrews)., Mar 1945-Apr 1945 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Cochran [?]: Report (contra Felix Morrow, on the International Political Situation). 50 pp., ca.1945 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Cochran: Speech re Labor Movement (hand-written), May 1945 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Morrison, M.: Why We Support the Struggle of the EAM (Greece), 4 pp., ca.1945 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Socialist Workers Party Correspondence (Includes: Cochran, Dobbs, Dunne), Nov 1945-Dec 1945 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Socialist Workers Party DocumentsContents: Discussion on the Black Question, by Murray Weiss; Proposal on the Functioning of the 4th International; Motion by Morrow on Italian Affiliation., 1945 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Socialist Workers Party Club Executive Minutes, Jan 1946-Apr 1946 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - SWP correspondence (Felix Morrow, et al), Feb 1946-Jun 1947 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Socialist Workers Party Club Executive Minutes (focus on Korea, Yugoslavia), May 1950-Jul 1950 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Socialist Workers Party National Committee Reports and Resolutions on Korea, Yugoslavia (Includes report on a trip to Yugoslavia), 1950 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Cochran Speech: The Revolution in Bolivia, Apr 24, 1953 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Cochran Speeches (2): U.S., International, ca.1953 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Cochran Speech: "What Is Going to Happen in the Next Ten Years?", 1955 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Cocharn Speeches: American Socialist Banquet, Other, 1955 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Cochran Speeches: Detroit, Los Angeles, San-Francisco, ca.1960 (Box 2, Folder 22)
- Series 2: Unpublished Writings.
  - Untitled Manuscript I (re Warfare in Human History), Ch. 7: Sword of Hellas, pp. 200-294, ca.1955-1964 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Untitled Manuscript I (re Warfare in Human History), Ch. 10: Ancient and Medieval Thought on War, and Ch. 11 - Faith of the Enlightment, pp. 307-377, ca.1955-1964 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Untitled Manuscript I (re Warfare in Human History), Ch. 12: The Return to Cults of Violence; Ch. 13: 19th Century Imperialism; Ch. 14: The Marxian Opposition, pp. 378-481, ca.1955-1964 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Untitled Manuscript I (re Warfare in Human History), Ch. 15: Roosevelt, Mahan, and Wilson; Ch. 16: Race and Reform; and Ch. 17: Conflict and Cooperation, pp. 482-573, ca.1955-1964 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Untitled Manuscript I (re Warfare in Human History), Ch. 18: Instinct and Civilization; and Ch. 19: Stages of Welfare, pp. 574-653., ca.1955-1964 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Untitled Manuscript II, Chapter 11: Workers and Intellectuals, pp. 521-556, ca.1978 (Box 3, Folder 6)
- Series 3: Addendum
  - Auto Workers: Draft Pamphlet and Noyes, 1939? (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Communist League of America: Internal Bulletin, 1933-1934 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Communist League of America: Internal Bulletin, 1934 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence: Cochran,Dobbs, Breitman, etc., 1953 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Communist Party Plenum (Stenogram), Jan 8, 1944 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Arnold Delbert and the CIO's Role in American Politics, 1936-1948, undated (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Document on the Unification of All Unemployed Organizations, 1935 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Frank, E.R., Memorandum on Resolution on "The Evolution of the Buffer Countries", undated (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Labor Writings, Clippings, etc., 1949 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Labor and the Multinationals, Cochran, undated (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Minutes of the International Secretariat, Dec 15, 1932 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - "Pabloist" Documents, 1950s (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Report: Meeting of Fisher Body (Cleveland Division) and UAW, Local 18614, Employees Cooperative Assn. and Mechanics Educational Society of America, 1934 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Shannon, David: Outline for Book on History of CPUSA, Feb 24, 1955 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Speech, undated (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Speech (Frank), undated (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Speech (Plenum), 1950 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Untitled Ms. Chapter 12 In the Perspective of History, undated (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Untitled Ms. Chapter 13, Variations on the Theme of Revolution, undated (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Untitled Ms. Notes 14 Italian Risorgimento, undated (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Workers Party of the US: Internal Bulletin, No.'s 1 and 2, 1935, 1936 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Workers Party: International Bulletin, 1935 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Workers Party of the US: Minutes, National Committee Plenum, Oct 1955 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Workers Party of the US: NC Plenum, Resolutions, Jun 1935 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Weatherhead Company: Transcript of Hearing re: Labor Matters (Cleveland, OH), 1937 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Photographs, reprints and originals: Labor and Communism #756, 1913-1976 (Box 5, Folder 11)